[
    {
        "question": "1. What is a shell script?",
        "answer": "A file containing a series of commands that are translated and carried out by a shell interpreter is known as a shell script. It enables task automation and command execution on an operating system with a Unix foundation.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "2. How is a shell script written?",
        "answer": "You must create a plain text file with the extension <file-name>.sh to construct a shell script. The script can be written using any text editor, such as vi, nano, or cat.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "3. Which command is used to execute a shell file?",
        "answer": "To execute a shell script (a text file containing shell commands), you typically use\n./script.sh extension.\nReplace “script.sh” with the actual name of your shell script.\nEnsure the script has executable permissions set using the following chmod command if needed:\nchmod +x script.sh\nThis makes the script executable, allowing you to run it using the ./ notation.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "4. Name the most commonly used shells on a typical Linux system.",
        "answer": "Linux shells primarily fall into two categories: C-shell and Bourne shell. Their derivatives are as follows:\nC-shell: TENEX C-Shell, Z-Shell\nBourne shell: Korn Shell, Bourne-Again Shell, POSIX Shell",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "5. Explain the difference between single quotes (') and double quotes (",
        "answer": "Here are the major differences between single quotes (‘) and double quotes (“) in shell scripting:\nParameter Single Quotes (‘) Double Quotes (“)\nVariable Substitution No variable substitution occurs inside single quotes. Variable substitution occurs inside double quotes.\nEscaping Special Characters Special characters within single quotes are treated as literal characters and not escaped. Special characters within double quotes can be escaped using a backslash ().\nCommand Substitution Command substitution is not allowed within single quotes. Command substitution (e.g., $(command)) is supported within double quotes.\nLiteral String Preservation Text enclosed in single quotes is treated as a literal string, preserving spaces and formatting. Text enclosed in double quotes is parsed, allowing variables and special characters to be interpreted.\nNested Quotes Nested single quotes within single quotes are not permitted. Nested double quotes within double quotes are permitted.\nWord Splitting Word splitting does not occur inside single quotes. Word splitting occurs inside double quotes, making it suitable for handling strings with spaces.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "6. What is the purpose of the case statement in shell scripting?",
        "answer": "The purpose of the case statement in shell scripting is to provide a structured and efficient way to perform conditional branching based on pattern matching. It simplifies decision-making by allowing the script to execute different code blocks for specific pattern matches, enhancing code readability.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "7. Define shell variable.",
        "answer": "A shell variable forms the core of a shell script or program. The variable enables the shell program to handle and manipulate stored information. It is generally stored as a string variable.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "8. What is the difference between $$ and $!?",
        "answer": "$$ and $! are both special variables in Unix-like operating systems$$ and $!\n$$: It represents the process ID (PID) of the currently executing shell or script.d .when you want to create temporary files with unique names to avoid naming conflicts.\n$!: It represents the PID of the last background process that was executed in the background using the & operator. It tracks background processes",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "9. What is a kernel?",
        "answer": "The kernel is a fundamental computer program within an operating system, responsible for overseeing and coordinating the operations of the computer and its hardware.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "10. How do you give a variable in a shell script a value?",
        "answer": "The variable_name=value format is used to assign values to variables in shell scripts. As an illustration, name=”John” gives the variable “name” the value “John”.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "11. How do you use conditional statements in a shell script?",
        "answer": "Conditional statements in shell scripting are typically made using the “if” statement. It follows the syntax if [ condition ]; then… fi. The “if” block commands are executed if the condition is true.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "12. How do you read input from the user in a shell script?",
        "answer": "In a shell script, the “read” command enables the user to capture input. It facilitates prompting the user for information and storing their response in a variable.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "13. How do you create a loop in a shell script?",
        "answer": "Shell scripts can use loops such as the “for” and “while” loops. The “for” loop is used to iterate over a sequence of values, whereas the “while” loop is used to repeat commands as long as a certain condition is true.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "14. Mention some limitations of shell scripting.",
        "answer": "Shell scripting has the following disadvantages:\nErrors are frequent and costly; a single error can alter the command.  \nThe execution speed is slow. \nBugs or inadequacies are in the language’s syntax or implementation.  \nLarge, complex tasks aren’t well suited to it.  \nContrary to other scripting languages, it provides a minimal data structure.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "15. What are is the absolute and relative paths?",
        "answer": "An absolute path provides the full file or directory location from the root directory, starting with / in Unix or a drive letter in Windows. A relative path specifies a location in relation to the current working directory, making it shorter and context-dependent.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "16. Elucidate the term shebang line.",
        "answer": "The term shebang line in shell scripting refers to the first line of a script that begins with #! followed by the path to the interpreter, such as /bin/bash. It specifies the interpreter to be used for executing the script. This line is crucial as it instructs the system on how to interpret and run the script, ensuring compatibility and proper execution.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "17. What are the various stages of the Linux process?",
        "answer": "In Linux, a process goes through several stages during its lifecycle:\nCreation: A process is created when a program is executed.\nReady: The process is ready to run but waiting for CPU time.\nRunning: The process is actively using the CPU.\nBlocked: The process is waiting for a specific event, such as I/O, to complete.\nTerminated: The process has completed its execution or was forcibly terminated.\n\nShell Scripting Programming Interview Questions for Experienced\nHere are a few of the intermediate-level interview questions for shell scripting for learners.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "18. How will you find the total number of shells available in your system?",
        "answer": "To determine the total number of shells available in a system through shell scripting, you can employ the following command: cat /etc/shells | wc -l. This command reads the /etc/shells file and uses the wc command to count the lines, which correspond to the available shells. Executing this command in your terminal will provide you with the desired information regarding the total number of shells available.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "19. Define control instructions.",
        "answer": "Control instructions in shell scripting are commands that dictate the flow and logic of a script. They include conditional statements (if-else), loops (for, while), and case statements, enabling precise program control. These instructions facilitate decision-making and repetitive tasks, enhancing script functionality and efficiency. Mastering control instructions is essential for effective shell scripting, empowering users to automate processes and manage data effectively.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "20. What is LILO?",
        "answer": "LILO (Linux Loader) is a legacy boot loader used in Linux systems. It manages the boot process by loading the Linux kernel into memory during system startup. However, it has been largely replaced by GRUB (GRand Unified Bootloader), which offers more features and flexibility in handling multiple operating systems and file systems.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "21. What do you mean by positional parameters in shell scripting?",
        "answer": "Positional parameters in shell scripting refer to variables that hold values passed to a script or function as command-line arguments. They are denoted by numbers, with $1 representing the first argument, $2 the second, and so on. These parameters enable dynamic input processing, enhancing script flexibility and functionality. Understanding positional parameters is fundamental for effective shell script development.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "22. How do you read input from a file line by line in a shell script?",
        "answer": "You can use a while loop with the read command to read input from a file line by line. For example:\nwhile IFS= read -r line; do\n    # Process each line here\ndone < input.txt",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "23. How do you handle errors and exceptions in a shell script?",
        "answer": "You can use the set -e option at the beginning of the script to exit immediately if any command returns a non-zero status (indicating an error). Additionally, you can use the trap command to catch and handle specific signals or errors within the script.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "24. How do you redirect the output of a command to a file and display it on the terminal simultaneously?",
        "answer": "You can use the tee command to achieve this. For example:\ncommand | tee output.txt\nGet 100% Hike!\nMaster Most in Demand Skills Now!\nBy providing your contact details, you agree to our Terms of Use & Privacy Policy",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "25. How do you compare two strings in a shell script?",
        "answer": "String comparison can be made using the double square brackets ([[ ]]) and the == operator. For example:\nif [[ $str1 == $str2 ]]; then\n    # Strings are equal\nfi",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "26. How do you schedule a shell script to run at a specific time using Cron?",
        "answer": "You can schedule a shell script using the crontab command. By editing the crontab file (crontab -e), you can specify the desired time and frequency for the script to run.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "27. What is the difference between $@ and $*?",
        "answer": "$* treats a group of positional arguments as one complete string, while $@ treats each quoted argument as an individual argument.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "28. How do you handle input validation and error checking in a shell script?",
        "answer": "You can use conditional statements (if and case) to validate input and check for errors. You can perform error handling and exit the script if necessary by using return codes ($?) and conditional checks.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "29. How do you create and use environment variables in a shell script?",
        "answer": "By assigning a value to a variable, you can create environment variables. For instance,\nMY_VARIABLE=\"Hello, World!\"\nexport MY_VARIABLE",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "30. How do you count the number of occurrences of a specific word in a file using shell scripting?",
        "answer": "You can use the grep command with the -c option to count the occurrences of a specific word in a file.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "31. How do you perform arithmetic calculations in shell scripting?",
        "answer": "Shell scripting supports arithmetic calculations using the expr command or double parentheses (( )) for arithmetic expansion. For example,\nresult=$(expr 2 + 2)\necho $result  # Outputs 4\n\nresult=$((2 + 2))\necho $result  # Outputs 4",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "32. What are CLIand GUI?",
        "answer": "CLI (Command Line Interface):\nText-based interface.\nEfficient for experienced users and scripting.\nCommon in Unix-like systems.\nRequires knowledge of specific commands.GUI (Graphical User Interface):\nVisual interface with icons and windows.\nUser-friendly and suitable for beginners.\nCommon in Windows, macOS, and desktop applications.\nReduces the need for memorizing commands.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "33. How will you will define whether the given link is hard or soft?",
        "answer": "In shell scripting, the categorization of a given link as hard or soft typically pertains to determining whether the link is symbolic or represents a physical file or directory. This can be accomplished using the ‘test’ command with the ‘-h’ flag, which returns true for symbolic links (soft) and false for actual files or directories (hard). Such distinctions aids in effective file management and scripting logic.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "34. What are the different types of variables in shell scripting?",
        "answer": "In shell scripting, there are three primary types of variables:\nLocal Variables: These are defined within a script and are only accessible within the script. Example: count=5.\nEnvironment Variables: These are available system-wide and can be accessed by any script or program. Example: PATH=”/usr/bin:/usr/local/bin”\nShell Variables: These are predefined by the shell and hold system information.\nExample:\n$HOME (user's home directory).\nThese variable types serve different purposes and scopes in shell scripting.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "35. What is the significance of $#?",
        "answer": "The significance of $# in shell scripting is that it represents the number of arguments passed to a script or function. It helps scriptwriters determine the count of positional parameters (arguments) provided when the script is executed. This information can be crucial for creating conditional logic based on the number of arguments or for iterating through and processing them within the script.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "36. Explain Crontab?",
        "answer": "Crontab is a Unix-based time scheduler for automating repetitive tasks. Users create “cron jobs” by specifying commands and defining when they should run based on a time schedule (minute, hour, day, month, day of the week). It allows users to automate tasks like backups, updates, and scripts at specified intervals. Each user can have their own crontab, and they can edit it using crontab -e. Crontab simplifies system maintenance and task automation on Unix-like systems.\n\nAdvanced Shell Scripting Interview Questions\nHere are some bash shell scripting interview questions for experienced developers:",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "37. Name two files of the crontab command.",
        "answer": "The two crontab command files are as follows:\ncron. deny: These files determine which user or users should be blocked from using the crontab command.\ncron. allow: These files determine which user or users should be granted permission to use the crontab command.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "38. How do you handle and process command-line options in a shell script?",
        "answer": "Command-line options can be handled using the getopts command or manually parsing the arguments. The getopts command provides a convenient way to specify and process options and their arguments.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "39. How do you securely handle sensitive information (like passwords) in a shell script?",
        "answer": "Sensitive information can be stored in environment variables or separate configuration files. You can restrict access to these files using proper file permissions and use tools like OpenSSL to encrypt or decrypt sensitive data.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "40. How do you work with arrays in a shell script?",
        "answer": "Arrays can be declared and accessed using square brackets and indexes. For example,\nmyarray=(\"apple\" \"banana\" \"cherry\")\necho \"${myarray[0]}\"  # Outputs \"apple\"",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "41. How do you calculate the execution time of a command or script in a shell script?",
        "answer": "You can use the time command to measure the execution time of a command or script. For example,\ntime ./myscript.sh",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "42. How do you process and manipulate text using regular expressions in a shell script?",
        "answer": "You can use the grep, sed, or awk commands with regular expressions to process and manipulate text in a shell script. Regular expressions provide powerful pattern-matching capabilities.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "43. What is the alternative to if-else if-else statements in bash?",
        "answer": "An alternative to an if-else if-else statement is a case statement. Its syntax differs from the switch case. The ‘case’ block is closed by ‘esac,’ and no break statement is used.\nSyntax:\ncase  in\nMatch pattern one) commands;\nMatch pattern two) commands;\nesac",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "44. How do you read and parse CSV or delimited files in a shell script?",
        "answer": "You can use the awk command with the appropriate field separator (-F) to parse CSV or delimited files. Alternatively, the cut or read command can extract specific columns.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "45. How do you handle concurrent processes or parallel execution in a shell script?",
        "answer": "Concurrent processes or parallel execution can be achieved using tools like xargs, parallel, or background processes, and job control operators (&, wait).",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "46. How do you debug shell scripts effectively?",
        "answer": "Effective debugging can be done using the set -x option to enable debugging mode, inserting echo statements to print intermediate values, using the trap command to catch and handle signals, and analyzing log files or error output.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "47. Differentiate between the grep and find commands.",
        "answer": "Parameter grep (Global Regular Expression Print) find\nFunctionality Searches for patterns within the content of files. Searches for files and directories in the file system hierarchy.\nFile Content Focuses on searching within file contents, making it suitable for text-based searches. Concentrates on locating files and directories based on metadata and attributes.\nOutput Displays lines containing matched patterns within files. Prints the paths of files and directories that meet specified criteria.\nUsage grep [options] pattern [file…] is used for text searches. find [path] [expression] is employed for file and directory searches.\nExamples grep -r “keyword” /path/to/search searches for “keyword” in files under the specified directory. find /path/to/search -name “*.txt” locates all “.txt” files under the given path.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "48. How do you use pipe commands in shell scripting?",
        "answer": "To utilize pipe commands in shell scripting, use the ‘|’ symbol to link multiple commands. This allows the output of one command to serve as the input for the next. For example, ‘command1 | command2’ directs the output of ‘command1’ as input to ‘command2’. This powerful technique streamlines tasks, enhances efficiency, and enables complex data processing in shell scripts, making it a valuable tool for system administrators and developers.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "49. Distinguish between the two most frequently employed shells in the Linux sSystem.",
        "answer": "There are mainly two kinds of Linux shells: C shell and Bourne shell.\nAspect C Shell (csh) Bourne Shell (sh)\nSyntax More C-like syntax with command history and tab completion Traditional and straightforward syntax\nScripting Language Primarily used for interactive tasks; limited scripting capabilities Designed for scripting with greater versatility\nControl Structures Supports ‘foreach’ and ‘while’ loops Offers ‘if-then-else’ statements and ‘for’ loops\nJob Control Robust job control for managing processes interactively Supports job control but less interactive",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "50. Differentiate between interactive and non-interactive shells.",
        "answer": "Parameter Interactive Non-Interactive\nDefinition Involves real-time, two-way communication where the system responds immediately to user input. Operates without real-time interaction, often following predefined instructions or scripts.\nUser Engagement Requires active user participation and responses during the interaction. Requires minimal or no user input once initiated.\nResponse Time Provides immediate responses to user actions, enhancing user engagement and control. Executes predefined tasks without expecting immediate user input, making it more automated.\nExamples Video conferencing, live chat support, video games, and virtual assistants that respond to voice commands. Batch processing, automated data analysis, and scheduled tasks like backups or system maintenance.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "51. What is the purpose of sed command and awk command?",
        "answer": "Parameter sed (Stream Editor) awk (Text Processing Tool)\nUsage Text manipulation in a linear, non-interactive manner Text processing with pattern scanning and processing\nFunctionality Primarily used for substitution, deletion, insertion, and more based on patterns More versatile, as it can perform complex text processing, including pattern matching, text extraction, and mathematical operations\nVariables Limited variable support for simple tasks Supports variables and arrays for complex data manipulation and storage\nLoops/Conditionals Lacks built-in loops and conditionals Supports loops, conditionals, and control structures for more intricate logic\nExamples sed ‘s/old/new/g’ file.txt replaces ‘old’ with ‘new’ globally in ‘file.txt’. awk ‘{ print $2 }’ file.txt prints the second field from each line in ‘file.txt’.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "52. What is a Hard Link?",
        "answer": "A hard link in shell scripting is a pointer directly to a file’s inode, there by giving the same file a different name. Hard links, as opposed to symbolic links, which point to filenames, point directly to the data within the file on the disk since they share the same inode. As long as there are still active hard links, deleting a file won’t get rid of its data or inode. Each file’s link count, which indicates the number of hard links connected to it, is displayed by the (ls -l )command. Hard links must be created within the same file system, and any changes made to the file through one hard link are immediately mirrored in all other hard links.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "53. What is Soft Link?",
        "answer": "A soft link, sometimes referred to as a symbolic link in shell scripting, is a unique form of a file that holds a path to another file or directory. Unlike hard links, symbolic links just provide a reference to the file’s location rather than actually pointing to the inode or file data. The symbolic link breaks if the original file is moved or deleted. Create shortcuts or aliases for files and folders using symbolic links to make it simpler to access them from other locations. They are able to link to files and directories in many file systems.\nUsing the (ln -s )command, one can create a symbolic link by supplying the target file or directory and the desired symbolic link name.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "54. When should shell programming/scripting not be used?",
        "answer": "Shell programming or scripting should not be used for complex software development tasks or applications that require high performance, extensive graphical interfaces, or intricate data manipulation. It is not suitable for projects demanding real-time processing, complex mathematical calculations, or sophisticated user interactions. Additionally, shell scripts may not be the best choice for large-scale applications with intricate architecture. In such cases, programming languages like Python, Java, C++, or specialized tools and frameworks are more appropriate for achieving better performance, maintainability, and scalability.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "55. What does the .(dot) indicate at the beginning of a file name and how should it be listed?",
        "answer": "A hidden file is one whose name starts with a . (dot). Every time we attempt to list the files, all files—hidden files excluded—are listed.\nIt will, however, be listed in the directory. Additionally, we must use the ls -a option, like $ ls -a, in order to list the hidden file.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "56. What are the different blocks of a file system? Explain in brief.",
        "answer": "The file system is divided into several core blocks or components, each of which serves a specific purpose in managing and storing the data efficiently. The files system’s main blocks are shown here:\nBoot Block: The first file system block with the bootstrap code or boot loader that must be installed in order to start your computer.\nSuperblock: A crucial data structure that offers crucial metadata about the file system, such as its type, size, status, list of free and used blocks, and more, including information on each block’s status. For mounting and using the file system, it is essential.\nBlock INODE: Each file or directory is represented by an inode (index node), which also contains metadata about the corresponding file, including permissions, timestamps, file size, and pointers to the data blocks. Inode blocks are collections of inodes. Blocks of data are the actual blocks that hold file data, including directory entries pointing to other files or subdirectories as well as file contents.\nFAT: File Allocation Table: a list that links the names of files to the corresponding inodes or data blocks. File systems like FAT and exFAT frequently use it.\nFDT: File Descriptor Table: a table with entries from the inode table that serve as file descriptors. It assists in managing open files and the data that goes with them.\nNo-cost block list: a list that manages the file system’s free or available blocks, allowing for the effective allocation of blocks for new files and directories.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "57. What is the alternative command available to echo and what does it do?",
        "answer": "tput is an alternative command to echo.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "58. How many types of control instructions are available in a shell? Explain in brief.",
        "answer": "In a shell, there are three types of control instructions:\nSequential Control: These instructions are executed one after the other in a sequential manner. They ensure that each command runs only after the previous one completes.\nConditional Control: Conditional instructions, like ‘if’ statements, enable decision-making in scripts. They execute commands based on specified conditions, allowing for branching and different outcomes.\nLoop Control: Loop instructions, such as ‘for’ and ‘while’ loops, repeatedly execute commands until a specified condition is met, providing automation and repetitive task handling.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "59. What is IFS?",
        "answer": "IFS stands for Internal Field Separator. And it is one of the system variables. By default, its value is space, tab, and a new line. It signifies that in a line where one field or word ends and another begins.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "60. What are the two files of the crontab command?",
        "answer": "The crontab command in Unix-like operating systems utilizes two files: the system-wide crontab file located at /etc/crontab and user-specific crontab files stored in /var/spool/cron/crontabs directory. The system-wide file is typically used by administrators for tasks that affect the entire system, while users employ their individual crontab files to schedule and manage recurring tasks specific to their accounts.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "61. What is Shebang in a shell script?",
        "answer": "Shebang is a hash sigh ‘#’ followed by an exclamation mark ‘!’ Generally, this can be seen at the beginning or top of the script/program. Usually, a developer uses this to avoid repetitive work. Shebang mainly determines the location of the engine which is to be used in order to execute the script.\nExample: #!/bin/bash\nThe above line also tells which shell to use.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "62. In shell scripting, where you will find the login names of all the users on a system, and how they can be printed at the same time?",
        "answer": "In shell scripting, you can find the login names of all users on a system by examining the “/etc/passwd” file, which contains user account information. To print all user login names simultaneously, you can use the “cut” command in combination with other commands like “awk” or “cut” to extract the necessary information. For instance, running “cut -d: -f1 /etc/passwd” will display a list of all user login names in the system.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "63. What do you know about the MBR in the shell scripting? How it is useful for the users?",
        "answer": "In shell scripting, MBR stands for Master Boot Record. It is a small but crucial data structure located in the first sector of a storage device, such as a hard drive. MBR contains information about the disk’s partitioning and the bootloader. It’s useful for users because it enables the system to boot, manage partitions, and load the operating system. Understanding and managing the MBR is essential for tasks like disk maintenance, repair, and dual-boot setups.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "64. What is the difference between process and thread?",
        "answer": "To put it in simple words, a thread is a small piece of code/instruction that needs to be executed in a process, whereas a process is a collection of one or more thread executions to complete one complete task.\nA process consists of multiple threads that can share resources among them as they belong to the same process. And threads that belong to different processes cannot share their resources.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "65. Without restarting the machine, how can we remove all the running processes?",
        "answer": "All the running processes in the current shell can be removed using the Linux killall command.",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "66. Command to wipe out variables defined.",
        "answer": "If we consider $ mm = 2018 as a variable defined by the user, then in order to wipe out the variable, the unset command is used.\nSyntax: $ unset mm",
        "reference": "intellipaat.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "1. What is the best way to run a script in the background?",
        "answer": "For a script to run in the background, simply add \"&\" at the end of the command. Example: Example: script.sh & command &",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "2. What is the use of the \"$?\" command?",
        "answer": "By using the command \"$?\", you can find out the status of the last command executed.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "3. How to check whether a link is a hard one or a soft link?",
        "answer": "We can use -h and -L operators of the test command to check whether a link is hard or soft (symbolic link). -h file      //true if the file is a symbolic link\n-L file      //true if the file is a symbolic link -h file      //true if the file is a symbolic link -h file      //true if the file is a symbolic link -L file      //true if the file is a symbolic link -L file      //true if the file is a symbolic link One can also use: readlink FILE; echo $?       // This returns 1 if it's a hard link and 0 if it's a symbolic link. readlink FILE; echo $?",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "4. Why is a shell script needed?",
        "answer": "Shell scripts can be written for a variety of reasons: Keeping repetitive tasks to a minimum.\nCan be used by system administrators for routine backups.\nMonitoring the system.\nAdding new functions to the shell.\nShell scripting allows you to create your own tools.\nSystem admin can automate daily tasks. Keeping repetitive tasks to a minimum. Can be used by system administrators for routine backups. Monitoring the system. Adding new functions to the shell. Shell scripting allows you to create your own tools. System admin can automate daily tasks.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "5. Write some advantages of shell scripting.",
        "answer": "Shell scripting offers the following benefits: An interactive debugging tool, as well as a quick start.   \nProgrammers need not change their syntax since both command and syntax are identical to those entered directly into the command line.  \nShell scripts are easy to use and quicker to write.   \nIt helps automate administrative tasks, so it is time-saving.   \nAs shell scripts are written in an interpreted language, they can be run without any additional effort on almost any modern operating system, including UNIX, Linux, BSD, and Mac OS X.  \nThey can be utilized for bulk execution rather than single instructions.   \nUsing it, you can develop your own custom operating system with relevant features.  \nSoftware applications can be developed according to their respective platforms with this tool. An interactive debugging tool, as well as a quick start. Programmers need not change their syntax since both command and syntax are identical to those entered directly into the command line. Shell scripts are easy to use and quicker to write. It helps automate administrative tasks, so it is time-saving. As shell scripts are written in an interpreted language, they can be run without any additional effort on almost any modern operating system, including UNIX, Linux, BSD, and Mac OS X. They can be utilized for bulk execution rather than single instructions. Using it, you can develop your own custom operating system with relevant features. Software applications can be developed according to their respective platforms with this tool.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "6. Write some limitations of shell scripting.",
        "answer": "Shell scripting has the following disadvantages: Errors are frequent and costly, and a single error can alter the command.  \nThe execution speed is slow. \nBugs or inadequacies in the language's syntax or implementation.  \nLarge, complex tasks aren't well suited to it.  \nContrary to other scripting languages, etc., it provides a minimal data structure.   \nEvery time a shell command is executed, a new process is launched. Errors are frequent and costly, and a single error can alter the command. The execution speed is slow. Bugs or inadequacies in the language's syntax or implementation. Large, complex tasks aren't well suited to it. Contrary to other scripting languages, etc., it provides a minimal data structure. Every time a shell command is executed, a new process is launched.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "7. Name the file in which shell programs are stored.",
        "answer": "A file called sh stores shell programs. Sh files contain commands written in a scripting language that is run by Unix shells.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "8. Name different types of shells available.",
        "answer": "Shells are divided into two categories: \nBourne shell: The $ character is the default prompt when using a Bourne-type shell.\nC shell: The % character is the default prompt when using a C-type shell. Shells are divided into two categories: \nBourne shell: The $ character is the default prompt when using a Bourne-type shell.\nC shell: The % character is the default prompt when using a C-type shell. Bourne shell: The $ character is the default prompt when using a Bourne-type shell.\nC shell: The % character is the default prompt when using a C-type shell. Bourne shell: The $ character is the default prompt when using a Bourne-type shell. Bourne shell: C shell: The % character is the default prompt when using a C-type shell. C shell: The Bourne-type is subdivided into the following categories: Bourne Again shell (BASH): This is the most common shell available on all Linux and based systems. It is open-source and freeware. In addition, it is an SH-compatible shell, with improved programming and interactive features over SH. It also allows you to efficiently perform many tasks.\nKorn shell (KSH): Korn is basically a Unix shell that was initially based on the Bash Shell Scripting. It's a high-level language that's quite advanced. It has associative arrays and handles the loop syntax better than Bash. It is basically an improved version of Bourne shell. Bourne Again shell (BASH): This is the most common shell available on all Linux and based systems. It is open-source and freeware. In addition, it is an SH-compatible shell, with improved programming and interactive features over SH. It also allows you to efficiently perform many tasks. Bourne Again shell (BASH): Korn shell (KSH): Korn is basically a Unix shell that was initially based on the Bash Shell Scripting. It's a high-level language that's quite advanced. It has associative arrays and handles the loop syntax better than Bash. It is basically an improved version of Bourne shell. Korn shell (KSH): The C-type is subdivided into the following categories: C shell (CSH): C shell is almost like C itself since it uses the shell syntax of the C programming language. In most cases, a command is executed either interactively from a terminal keyboard or from a file.\nTENEX/TOPS C shell (TCSH): TCSH does not have a specific full name. TCSH is considered as an enhanced version of the CSH as it includes some additional features over CSH like command-line editing and filename or command completion. As with the previous version, it supports C-style syntax also. C shell (CSH): C shell is almost like C itself since it uses the shell syntax of the C programming language. In most cases, a command is executed either interactively from a terminal keyboard or from a file. C shell (CSH): TENEX/TOPS C shell (TCSH): TCSH does not have a specific full name. TCSH is considered as an enhanced version of the CSH as it includes some additional features over CSH like command-line editing and filename or command completion. As with the previous version, it supports C-style syntax also. TENEX/TOPS C shell (TCSH):",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "9. Write difference between Bourne Shell and C Shell.",
        "answer": "Bourne Shell: It has compactness and speed that set it apart from other shells. But it lacks interactive features such as the ability to recall previous commands. Additionally, the Bourne shell does not support arithmetic and logical expressions.\nC Shell: It is a UNIX enhancement that incorporates interactive features like aliases and history of commands. Besides its built-in arithmetic and expression syntax, it also includes convenient programming features. Bourne Shell: It has compactness and speed that set it apart from other shells. But it lacks interactive features such as the ability to recall previous commands. Additionally, the Bourne shell does not support arithmetic and logical expressions. Bourne Shell: C Shell: It is a UNIX enhancement that incorporates interactive features like aliases and history of commands. Besides its built-in arithmetic and expression syntax, it also includes convenient programming features. C Shell: Difference between Bourne shell and C shell Difference between Bourne shell and C shell The C shell allows you to alias commands easily, whereas Bourne Shell does not allow this.\nIn the C shell, long commands can be used repeatedly, but not in Bourne.\nBourne does not have access to the command history, but the C shell does.\nIn the case of C, there is no need to repeatedly type the command. The C shell allows you to alias commands easily, whereas Bourne Shell does not allow this. In the C shell, long commands can be used repeatedly, but not in Bourne. Bourne does not have access to the command history, but the C shell does. In the case of C, there is no need to repeatedly type the command.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "10. What do you mean by Shell variable?",
        "answer": "Shell variables are integral parts of all Shell programs and scripts. In general, we know that variables usually store data either in the form of characters or numbers. Shell also stores and manipulates information using variables in its programs. Generally, shell variables are stored as strings. Variables in the shell provide the information needed for scripts/commands to execute. In the following example, a shell variable is created and then printed: \n\nvariable =\"Hello\" \necho $variable   ",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "11. What are different types of variables mostly used in shell scripting?",
        "answer": "Shell scripts usually have two types of variables: System-defined variables: Also called environment variables, these are special built-in variables in the Linux kernel for each shell. They are normally defined in capital letters by the OS (Linux) and are standard variables.\nExample:  \nSHELL  \nIt is a Unix Defined or System Variable, which specifies the default working shell. \nUser-defined variables: These variables are created and defined by users in order to store, access, read, and manipulate data. In general, they are defined in lowercase letters. The Echo command allows you to view them.\nExample:    \n$ a=10 \nIn this case, the user has defined the variable ‘a’ and assigned it the value 10. System-defined variables: Also called environment variables, these are special built-in variables in the Linux kernel for each shell. They are normally defined in capital letters by the OS (Linux) and are standard variables.\nExample:  \nSHELL  \nIt is a Unix Defined or System Variable, which specifies the default working shell. System-defined variables:  Example:   User-defined variables: These variables are created and defined by users in order to store, access, read, and manipulate data. In general, they are defined in lowercase letters. The Echo command allows you to view them.\nExample:    \n$ a=10 \nIn this case, the user has defined the variable ‘a’ and assigned it the value 10. User-defined variables:  Example:  ",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "12. Explain the term positional parameters.",
        "answer": "In a shell program, positional parameters specify arguments that are used to launch the current process. A special set of variables is usually maintained by the shell for storing positional parameter values. Bash is an example of a shell that uses positional parameters. The bash shell can be used on Linux, BSD, macOS X, and Windows 10. For example: For example: mycommand one five \"six four” In this case, the command name is mycommand, and there are four parameters in the command line: one, five, and \"six four”. Note: A space delimits each positional parameter and each thing after spaces are interpreted by the shell as individual parameters. Therefore, the parameter itself should be enclosed in quotation marks if it contains a space, as in \"six four\". Note:",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "13. What are control instructions?",
        "answer": "Control instructions specify how the different instructions will be executed in the script. They are primarily used to determine the control flow in Shell programs. The execution of a shell script proceeds in succession without these instructions. In shell programs, control instructions govern how execution flows.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "14. How many types of control instructions are available in a shell?",
        "answer": "Shells provide four types of control instructions as given below: Sequence Control Instruction: This assures that a program's command runs in the sequence they are listed. As soon as the first command in the sequence has been completed, the second command follows, and so on.\nDecision Control Instruction: It is also known as Selection Control Instruction. This instructs the computer which instruction it should execute next. In this, checking a condition is the basis for deciding which section to execute. If a given condition is True, a statement or set of statements will be executed; otherwise, they will be ignored.\nLoop Control Instruction: It is also known as Repetition Instruction. This instruction allows a computer to continuously run a particular sequence of code. In a loop structure, the statements can be repeated until a condition is True or False, a particular number of times, or once for each element within the collection\nCase-Control Instruction: This is used for selecting among several choices. Typically, they are used to execute only a particular block of statements within a series of statements. Sequence Control Instruction: This assures that a program's command runs in the sequence they are listed. As soon as the first command in the sequence has been completed, the second command follows, and so on. Sequence Control Instruction: Decision Control Instruction: It is also known as Selection Control Instruction. This instructs the computer which instruction it should execute next. In this, checking a condition is the basis for deciding which section to execute. If a given condition is True, a statement or set of statements will be executed; otherwise, they will be ignored. Decision Control Instruction: Loop Control Instruction: It is also known as Repetition Instruction. This instruction allows a computer to continuously run a particular sequence of code. In a loop structure, the statements can be repeated until a condition is True or False, a particular number of times, or once for each element within the collection Loop Control Instruction: Case-Control Instruction: This is used for selecting among several choices. Typically, they are used to execute only a particular block of statements within a series of statements. Case-Control Instruction:",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "15. Explain ways to create shortcuts in Linux.",
        "answer": "Links present in Linux OS can be used to create shortcuts as given below: Linux Hard Link: Hard links are mirror images of the originally linked files and are linked with an inode number. A hard-linked file remains even after the original file is deleted. Since hard links point to inodes, they cannot be implemented on directories. Hard links are created by the following command: Hard Link: Hard links are mirror images of the originally linked files and are linked with an inode number. A hard-linked file remains even after the original file is deleted. Since hard links point to inodes, they cannot be implemented on directories. Hard links are created by the following command: Hard Link: $ ln  [original filename] [link name] $ ln  [original filename] [link name]   Soft Link: Generally, soft links (also referred to as Symbolic links) are linked to the file name and can reside on the same as well as different file systems. When a soft link is created or deleted, it does not affect the original file, but when the original file is deleted, the soft link stops working. Typically, soft links are aliases (alternative paths) for the original file. Soft links are created by the following command: Soft Link: Generally, soft links (also referred to as Symbolic links) are linked to the file name and can reside on the same as well as different file systems. When a soft link is created or deleted, it does not affect the original file, but when the original file is deleted, the soft link stops working. Typically, soft links are aliases (alternative paths) for the original file. Soft links are created by the following command: Soft Link: $ ln  -s [original filename] [link name] $ ln  -s [original filename] [link name]",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "16. What is Shell?",
        "answer": "A Shell is basically a command-line interpreter between user and kernel or a complete environment specially designed to run commands, shell scripts, and programs. In this, whenever a user enters human-readable commands (input commands) through the keyboard, the shell communicates with the kernel to execute these commands, and display output in a shell script. Just as there are different flavors of operating systems, there are also different types of shells. Every shell has its own set of commands and functions. Shells issue the prompt, $, called a command prompt. You can type into the prompt while it is displayed. After you press enter, your input is read by the shell. Based on the first word of your input, it determines the command you want to run. The characters in a word are separated using spaces and tabs. Example: Example: Here is an example of a date command that displays the current date and time: $date Tue Aug 10 06:03:35 MST 2021 $date Tue Aug 10 06:03:35 MST 2021  ",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "17. Write difference between Hard link and Soft Link.",
        "answer": "Hard Link Soft Link\nHard-linked files have the same inode number.  Soft-linked files have different inode numbers.\nDespite deleting the target file, it remains valid. When an original file is deleted, it becomes invalid.\nHard links are faster than soft links.  Soft links are slower than hard links.\nThe command used for creating a hard link in Linux is \"ln\".   The command used for creating a soft link in Linux is “ln -s”.\nThere is no way to use it across file systems.   You can use it on any file system.\nHard links cannot use relative paths.  Both absolute and relative paths can be used in soft links. Hard Link Soft Link\nHard-linked files have the same inode number.  Soft-linked files have different inode numbers.\nDespite deleting the target file, it remains valid. When an original file is deleted, it becomes invalid.\nHard links are faster than soft links.  Soft links are slower than hard links.\nThe command used for creating a hard link in Linux is \"ln\".   The command used for creating a soft link in Linux is “ln -s”.\nThere is no way to use it across file systems.   You can use it on any file system.\nHard links cannot use relative paths.  Both absolute and relative paths can be used in soft links. Hard Link Soft Link Hard Link Soft Link Hard Link Soft Link Hard-linked files have the same inode number.  Soft-linked files have different inode numbers.\nDespite deleting the target file, it remains valid. When an original file is deleted, it becomes invalid.\nHard links are faster than soft links.  Soft links are slower than hard links.\nThe command used for creating a hard link in Linux is \"ln\".   The command used for creating a soft link in Linux is “ln -s”.\nThere is no way to use it across file systems.   You can use it on any file system.\nHard links cannot use relative paths.  Both absolute and relative paths can be used in soft links. Hard-linked files have the same inode number.  Soft-linked files have different inode numbers. Hard-linked files have the same inode number. Soft-linked files have different inode numbers. Despite deleting the target file, it remains valid. When an original file is deleted, it becomes invalid. Despite deleting the target file, it remains valid. When an original file is deleted, it becomes invalid. Hard links are faster than soft links.  Soft links are slower than hard links. Hard links are faster than soft links. Soft links are slower than hard links. The command used for creating a hard link in Linux is \"ln\".   The command used for creating a soft link in Linux is “ln -s”. The command used for creating a hard link in Linux is \"ln\". The command used for creating a soft link in Linux is “ln -s”. There is no way to use it across file systems.   You can use it on any file system. There is no way to use it across file systems. You can use it on any file system. Hard links cannot use relative paths.  Both absolute and relative paths can be used in soft links. Hard links cannot use relative paths. Both absolute and relative paths can be used in soft links.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "18. What do you mean by GUI Scripting?",
        "answer": "The GUI (Graphical User Interface) is a client/server interface that uses graphical icons and visual indicators to allow users to interact with devices. Specifically, it is used to control a computer and its applications. A wide variety of applications are supported, and it is largely dependent on the operating system.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "19. What is the shebang line in shell scripting?",
        "answer": "Shell scripts or programs often contain shebang at the top. In general, the Shebang (the series of characters \"#!\") is used to indicate the operating system to use a particular interpreter to process the rest of the file. Here, the symbol '#' is referred to as hash, and \"!\" is referred to as bang. This usually aids developers in avoiding repetitive work. Scripts are generally executed by the engine; therefore, shebang determines the location of the engine that will be used to run the script. Example: Example: #!/bin/bash In addition, this line also specifies which shell to use.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "20. What is a file system? Write down the four core components of a Linux file system.",
        "answer": "Generally, file systems are referred to as the collections of files, which include information related to those files. It would be impossible to tell where one piece of data stops and the next begins without a file system. There are four blocks in a file system: Super Block: A superblock contains information about a file system, including block size, group size, usage statistics, empty/filled blocks, inode table size & location, and so on. One of the tools used to describe a file system, along with inodes, entries, and files, is the superblock. Multiple superblocks are created with the file system, as the superblock contains critical information.  \nBoot Block: Located on the disk label, a boot block is a special set of blocks that contains data or information on the disk layout. Normally, this block contains the bootstrap loader program, which a user runs upon launching the host computer. The boot block remains blank if the file system is not used for boot.    \nData Block: Also called storage blocks, data blocks contain the remainder of the space allocated to the file system. The data block's size is measured at the time of file system creation. For a regular file, the content of files is contained in the data blocks. For directories, the inode number and file name of the files are contained in the data blocks.  \nInode: Inodes contain information about each file in the filesystem. Normally, an inode doesn't contain a file's name, which is located in a directory instead.  An inode contains information such as the type of file, the permission bits, the owner, the group, the file size, and the time when the file was modified. Super Block: A superblock contains information about a file system, including block size, group size, usage statistics, empty/filled blocks, inode table size & location, and so on. One of the tools used to describe a file system, along with inodes, entries, and files, is the superblock. Multiple superblocks are created with the file system, as the superblock contains critical information. Super Block: Boot Block: Located on the disk label, a boot block is a special set of blocks that contains data or information on the disk layout. Normally, this block contains the bootstrap loader program, which a user runs upon launching the host computer. The boot block remains blank if the file system is not used for boot. Boot Block: Data Block: Also called storage blocks, data blocks contain the remainder of the space allocated to the file system. The data block's size is measured at the time of file system creation. For a regular file, the content of files is contained in the data blocks. For directories, the inode number and file name of the files are contained in the data blocks. Data Block: Inode: Inodes contain information about each file in the filesystem. Normally, an inode doesn't contain a file's name, which is located in a directory instead.  An inode contains information such as the type of file, the permission bits, the owner, the group, the file size, and the time when the file was modified. Inode:",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "21. Name the alternative command for echo.",
        "answer": "The tput command is an alternative command for echo. We can use this command to control how the output is displayed.  Additionally, shell scripts can do things such as underline text and center text, regardless of the size of the screen.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "22. Explain the way you can connect to a database server.",
        "answer": "Open client driver comes with the isql utility that can be used to connect to a database server from Linux. Here's how to do it: isql –S serverName –U username –P password isql –S serverName –U username –P password",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "23. What is the importance of $#?",
        "answer": "$# usually holds the number of arguments, although it may be different for functions. To put it simply, it was used to store the number of command-line arguments passed to a shell script.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "24. Write the command that is used to execute a shell file.",
        "answer": "Firstly, use the chmod command to set execute permission on your script as shown below: chmod +x script-name-here.sh chmod +x script-name-here.sh Secondly, run or execute your script as follows: ./script-name-here.sh /script-name-here.sh Alternatively, you can execute shell script by: sh script-name-here.sh sh script-name-here.sh",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "25. Name the command that can be used to find out the number of arguments passed to the script?",
        "answer": "The following command will display the number of arguments passed to the script: echo $ # echo $ #",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "26. How long does a variable in a shell script last?",
        "answer": "Variables inside shell scripts have a lifespan of only as long as the execution lasts.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "27. What does the . (dot) indicate at the beginning of the file name? How can it be listed?",
        "answer": "If the file name begins with \".\", it is a hidden file. When a dot appears at the beginning of a filename, the file is hidden in most file managers and shell programs. A Shell usually lists all the files except hidden files when you try to list the files in a shell. Despite this, hidden files can be found in the directory. The Is command must be run with the \"–a\" flag if you wish to see hidden files.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "1. What is the importance of sed command and awk command?",
        "answer": "sed Command: sed command is an acronym for stream editor. It is used for editing a file without using an editor. The SED command performs a variety of operations on files, such as searching, finding and replacing, inserting and deleting. However, substitution or find and replace are the most commonly used features of SED.\nSyntax: sed options file \nExample: Execution over Shell Interpreter/Editor sed Command: sed command is an acronym for stream editor. It is used for editing a file without using an editor. The SED command performs a variety of operations on files, such as searching, finding and replacing, inserting and deleting. However, substitution or find and replace are the most commonly used features of SED.\nSyntax: sed options file \nExample: Execution over Shell Interpreter/Editor sed Command:  Syntax:  Example: /u/user1/Shell_Scripts_2020> echo \"Hi Gourav\" | sed 's/Hi/Hello/' /u/user1/Shell_Scripts_2020> echo \"Hi Gourav\" | sed 's/Hi/Hello/' In this case, “s” command in sed replaces the string Hi with “Hello”. Output: Output: Hello Gourav Hello Gourav awk Command: The command is a scripting language generally used to manipulate data and generate reports. There is no need to compile it and users are allowed to have access to a variable, string functions, numeric functions, and logical operations.\nSyntax: awk options File Name \nExample: Script/Code awk Command: The command is a scripting language generally used to manipulate data and generate reports. There is no need to compile it and users are allowed to have access to a variable, string functions, numeric functions, and logical operations.\nSyntax: awk options File Name \nExample: Script/Code awk Command:  Syntax:  Example: /u/user1/Shell_Scripts_2017> cat > script10 \nHello Aisha \nHello Rohan \nHello Gourav /u/user1/Shell_Scripts_2017> cat > script10 \nHello Aisha \nHello Rohan \nHello Gourav An awk command/utility assigns variables in following way: $0 -> For whole line (e.g. Hello Aisha) $1 -> For the first field i.e. Hello $2 -> For the second field Execution over Shell Interpreter/Editor Execution over Shell Interpreter/Editor awk ‘{print $0}’ script10 awk ‘{print $0}’ script10 The above script prints all the 3 lines completely. Output: Output: Hello Aisha \nHello Rohan \nHello Gourav Hello Aisha \nHello Rohan \nHello Gourav Execution over Shell Interpreter/Editor Execution over Shell Interpreter/Editor awk ‘{print $1}’ script10 awk ‘{print $1}’ script10 The above script prints only the first word i.e., Hello from each line. Output: Output: Hello \nHello \nHello Hello \nHello \nHello",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "2. What do you mean by crontab?",
        "answer": "Crontab stands for \"cron table,\" meaning that it makes use of the cron scheduler to perform tasks. In other words, it is the list of commands that you wish to run on a regular schedule and the command that will let you manage it. It is possible to view or edit the table of commands using the crontab command. In addition to the schedule, the term \"Crontab\" also refers to the name of the program used to edit the schedule.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "3. Name two files of crontab command.",
        "answer": "cron.deny and cron.allow are two files in the /etc/cron.d directory that controls access to the crontab command. Crontab command tasks such as creating, editing, displaying, or removing crontab files are relegated to specific users through these files. Both files usually consist of a list of user names, one user name per line. Together, these access control files perform the following functions: cron.deny cron.allow cron.allow decides which users are allowed to run the crontab command.\ncron.deny decides which users are denied from using the crontab command.\nWhen cron.allow or cron.deny doesn't exist, superuser privileges are required to run it. cron.allow decides which users are allowed to run the crontab command. cron.deny decides which users are denied from using the crontab command. When cron.allow or cron.deny doesn't exist, superuser privileges are required to run it.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "4. Name the command that is used to take the backup.",
        "answer": "The backup is taken using the tar command. Tar is an acronym for tape archive and is used to create backups using tar, gzip, and bzip. Files can be saved and restored from and to a tape using this command. In this, files and directories are generally compressed into tarballs, an archive file. For this purpose, it is among the most widely used commands. Furthermore, the tarball can be easily moved from one server to another.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "5. Write the difference between $* and $@",
        "answer": "Unlike $@, where each quoted argument is treated as a separate argument, $* treats each positional parameter as a single argument.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "6. Name the command that is used to compare the strings in a shell script.",
        "answer": "To compare text strings, use the test command. By comparing each character in each string, the test command usually compares text strings.  In most cases, tests are generally included as a conditional execution of shell commands. It can be used for: Comparison of file attributes\nComparison of strings\nComparing basic arithmetic operations Comparison of file attributes Comparison of strings Comparing basic arithmetic operations Using square brackets ([ and ]) around the EXPRESSION is equivalent to testing it with the test. Syntax of test command: Syntax of test command: test EXPRESSION\ntest EXPRESSION && true-command\ntest EXPRESSION || false-command\ntest EXPRESSION && true-command || false-command test EXPRESSION test EXPRESSION && true-command test EXPRESSION || false-command test EXPRESSION && true-command || false-command Examples: Examples: test 50 -gt 40 && echo \"Yes\" || echo \"No\" test 50 -gt 40 && echo \"Yes\" || echo \"No\" Because 50 is greater than 40, this command prints the text \"Yes\". [\"Excellent\" = \"Excellent\"]; echo $? [\"Excellent\" = \"Excellent\"]; echo $? As the two strings are identical, this command prints \"0\" because the expression is true.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "7. Write down the Syntax for all the loops in Shell Scripting.",
        "answer": "In shell scripting, you can use three looping statements as given below: while statement\nfor statement\nuntil statement while statement for statement until statement Syntax is as follows: Syntax is as follows: For Loop: Loops that operate on lists of items are known as loops. Each item in the list receives the same set of commands. For Loop: Loops that operate on lists of items are known as loops. Each item in the list receives the same set of commands. For Loop: Syntax: Syntax: for var in word1 word2 ... wordN \ndo   \n        Statement to be executed  \ndone for var in word1 word2 ... wordN \ndo   \n        Statement to be executed  \ndone Example: Example: for a in 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 \ndo \n    if [ $a == 3 ] \n    then \n        break \n    fi \n    echo \"Iteration no $a\" \ndone for a in 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 \ndo \n    if [ $a == 3 ] \n    then \n        break \n    fi \n    echo \"Iteration no $a\" \ndone Output” Output” $bash -f main.sh \nIteration no 1 \nIteration no 2 $bash -f main.sh \nIteration no 1 \nIteration no 2 While Loop: It involves evaluating a command first and then executing a loop based on the result. The loop will be terminated if the command raises to false. While Loop: It involves evaluating a command first and then executing a loop based on the result. The loop will be terminated if the command raises to false. While Loop: Syntax: Syntax:   while command \ndo \n    Statement to be executed \ndone while command \ndo \n    Statement to be executed \ndone Example: Example: a=0 \nwhile [ $a -lt 3 ] \ndo  \n    echo $a \n    a=`expr $a + 1` \ndone a=0 \nwhile [ $a -lt 3 ] \ndo  \n    echo $a \n    a=`expr $a + 1` \ndone Output: Output: $bash -f main.sh \n0 \n1 \n2 \n3 $bash -f main.sh \n0 \n1 \n2 \n3 Until Loop: As often as the condition/command evaluates to false, the until loop is executed. Once the condition or command becomes true, the loop terminates. Until Loop: As often as the condition/command evaluates to false, the until loop is executed. Once the condition or command becomes true, the loop terminates. Until Loop: Syntax: Syntax: until command \ndo  \n         Statement to be executed until command is true \ndone until command \ndo  \n         Statement to be executed until command is true \ndone Example: Example: a=0 \nuntil [ $a -gt 3 ] \ndo  \n    echo $a \n    a=`expr $a + 1` \ndone a=0 \nuntil [ $a -gt 3 ] \ndo  \n    echo $a \n    a=`expr $a + 1` \ndone Output: Output: $bash -f main.sh \n0 \n1 \n2 \n3 $bash -f main.sh \n0 \n1 \n2 \n3",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "8. What are interactive and non-interactive shells?",
        "answer": "Interactive shell: /bin/bash and /bin/sh is interactive shell. It is a non-login shell that gets started from a command line. It first copies the parent environment and then invokes. Interactive shell: /bin/bash and /bin/sh Non-Interactive shell: /sbin/nologin shell is non-interactive shell. It is present when the shell script is running and just inherits the parent's environment. Non-Interactive shell: /sbin/nologin",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "9. How will you pass and access arguments to a script in Linux?",
        "answer": "In scripts, arguments are passed as follows: scriptName \"Arg1\" \"Arg2\"….\"Argn\" Arguments in a script can be accessed as follows: $1 , $2 .. $n",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "10. What do you mean by the “s” permission bit in a file?",
        "answer": "The SUID (Set User ID) bit is known as the \"s\" bit. SUIDS are special file permissions for executable files that enable other users to run the file as the file owner. There will be an s (to indicate SUID) special permission for the user instead of the normal x, which represents execute permissions. A file that has the \"s\" bit set will grant the process the rights of the file's owner while the program is running. Example: Example: Executing the \"passwd\" command to change the password, for example, allows the user to write the new password to the shadow file even though its owner is \"root\".",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "11. How will you debug a shell script?",
        "answer": "With set, you can turn on or off debugging options in the shell: Set -x: This displays commands and their arguments as they are being executed.\nSet -v: It displays shell input lines in real-time as they are read. Set -x: This displays commands and their arguments as they are being executed. Set -x: Set -v: It displays shell input lines in real-time as they are read. Set -v:",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "12. What is the best way to debug the shell script/program problems?",
        "answer": "Following are some common methods of debugging a script: The shell script can be modified to include debug statements to display the information that can be useful in identifying the problem.   \nBy setting -x in the script, we can enable debugging. The shell script can be modified to include debug statements to display the information that can be useful in identifying the problem. By setting -x in the script, we can enable debugging.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "13. Write the difference between “=” and “==”.",
        "answer": "= operator: Assigning the value into a variable is accomplished by using the = operator. It is referred to as the assignment operator.\nExample: Suppose variable a holds 5 and variable b holds 2, then: = operator: Assigning the value into a variable is accomplished by using the = operator. It is referred to as the assignment operator.\nExample: Suppose variable a holds 5 and variable b holds 2, then: = operator:  Example: a = $b;              #Would assign value of b to a a = $b;              #Would assign value of b to a == operator: This is used to compare strings. In the double equals operator, both operands are compared. If they are equal, it returns true, otherwise, it returns false.\nExample: Suppose variable a holds 5 and variable b holds 2, then: == operator: This is used to compare strings. In the double equals operator, both operands are compared. If they are equal, it returns true, otherwise, it returns false.\nExample: Suppose variable a holds 5 and variable b holds 2, then: == operator:  Example [ $a == $b ];      #Comparing the values of a and b. [ $a == $b ];      #Comparing the values of a and b.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "14. Name the command that is used to display the shell's environment variable.",
        "answer": "Shell functions, along with other Linux programs, are controlled by environmental variables.   Any child process of the shell has access to an environment variable. These variables are necessary for some programs to function properly. env or printenv commands can be used to display the shell's environment variables. env printenv ",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "15. Name different commands that are available to check the disk usage.",
        "answer": "The following commands are available to check disk space usage: df – It is used to find out how much space is left on a disk.\ndu – With this command, you can find out how much disk space the specified files and each subdirectory take up.\ndfspace – Using this command, you can check the amount of free disk space in MB. df – It is used to find out how much space is left on a disk. df du – With this command, you can find out how much disk space the specified files and each subdirectory take up. du dfspace – Using this command, you can check the amount of free disk space in MB. dfspace",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "16. What do you mean by metacharacters?",
        "answer": "In a data field or program, metacharacters are special characters that provide information about other characters. In shells, they're called regular expressions.  A character that is neither a letter nor a number is generally considered a metacharacter. Using shell metacharacters, you can group together commands, redirect and pipe input/output, put commands in the background, reduce the size of file names and path names, etc. You can use them as wildcards to specify a file name without typing in the file's full name. The most common metacharacters are as follows: Asterisk (*): Use the * to match any character.\nQuestion Mark (?): It matches a single character in the filename.\nBrackets ([…]):  The metacharacters used here match some specified characters.\nHyphen (-): When placed within [] (brackets), the - metacharacter matches a specified range. Asterisk (*): Use the * to match any character. Asterisk (*) Question Mark (?): It matches a single character in the filename. Question Mark (?): Brackets ([…]):  The metacharacters used here match some specified characters. Brackets ([…]): Hyphen (-): When placed within [] (brackets), the - metacharacter matches a specified range. Hyphen (-):",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "17. How will you find total shells available in your system?",
        "answer": "Within your system, there are several shells available. If you want to find all the shells on the system, you can use $ cat /etc/shells. Example: Example: $ cat /etc/shells Execution over Shell Interpreter/Editor: Execution over Shell Interpreter/Editor: $ cat /etc/shells Output: Output: /bin/sh /bin/bash /sbin/nologin /bin/ksh /bin/csh",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "18. Explain how you will open a read-only file in Unix/Shell.",
        "answer": "You can open a read-only file by: vi –R <Filename> vi –R <Filename>",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "19. Name the command that one should use to know how long the system has been running.",
        "answer": "Using the Uptime command, you can see how long your system has been active. You can also determine the number of users with running sessions, and the average system load for 1, 5, and 15 minutes. The information displayed at once can also be filtered based on your specified options. Example: $ uptime Example: $ uptime Entering the above command at the shell prompt, namely $ uptime, will produce the following output: 9:21am  up 86 day(s), 11:46,  3 users,  load average: 2.24, 2.18, 2.16",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "20. Write the difference between $$ and $!?",
        "answer": "You can use $$ to get the process id of the current process. However, $! displays the process id for a background process that recently went away.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "21. Write difference between grep and find command.",
        "answer": "Grep command: This command facilitates searching and displaying content based on regular expressions specified by the user. Using the Grep command, one can search in a file for patterns. Grep command have the following syntax:\ngrep “literal string” <filename> Grep command: This command facilitates searching and displaying content based on regular expressions specified by the user. Using the Grep command, one can search in a file for patterns. Grep command have the following syntax:\ngrep “literal string” <filename> Grep command:  grep “literal string” <filename> Example: Example: grep “apple” file1.txt                     //Displays all the lines with the word “apple” in the file1\n\ngrep “apple” file1.txt  file2.txt   //Scan multiple documents and search the word “apple” in both files. grep “apple” file1.txt                     //Displays all the lines with the word “apple” in the file1\n\ngrep “apple” file1.txt  file2.txt   //Scan multiple documents and search the word “apple” in both files. Find command: The FIND command searches for files and folders based on their size, modification time, and access time. You can use this command to search files and directories. Find command have the following syntax:\nfind <path> <search criteria> <action> Find command: The FIND command searches for files and folders based on their size, modification time, and access time. You can use this command to search files and directories. Find command have the following syntax:\nfind <path> <search criteria> <action> Find command:  find <path> <search criteria> <action> Example: Example: find –type  f                      // Command will find all the files\n\nfind  –type  d                    //Command will find all the directories\n\nfind .  –name file1.txt       //Command will find file1.txt in the current directory. find –type  f                      // Command will find all the files\n\nfind  –type  d                    //Command will find all the directories\n\nfind .  –name file1.txt       //Command will find file1.txt in the current directory.",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "22. How can we create a function in shell script?",
        "answer": "In other programming languages, shell functions are much like subroutines, procedures, and functions. The syntax for declaring a function is as follows: function_name () \n{ \n   list of commands\n} function_name () \n{ \n   list of commands\n} Function_name is the name of your function, and that's what you'll use to call it from anywhere in your script. The function name must be followed by parentheses, then a list of commands enclosed in braces. Example: Example: The following example shows how function can be used: #!/bin/sh\n# Define your function here\n \nHello () \n  {\n     echo \"Hello World\"\n  }\n \n# Invoke your function\nHello #!/bin/sh\n# Define your function here\n \nHello () \n  {\n     echo \"Hello World\"\n  }\n \n# Invoke your function\nHello The following output will be displayed after execution: $./test.sh\nHello World $./test.sh\nHello World",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "23. How to use pipe commands?",
        "answer": "Pipe command allows you to use several commands in the same way, in which the output of one is used as input for another. Like a pipeline, each process output is directly input to the next one. A pipe is represented by the symbol \"|\". The flow of data through a pipeline is unidirectional, i.e., from left to right. Syntax : Syntax : command_1 | command_2 | command_3 | .... | command_N command_1 | command_2 | command_3 | .... | command_N Conclusion Conclusion You can automate a lot of repetitive manual tasks with shell scripting, which is an easy and powerful programming method. Modern programming languages offer many of the features that make them appealing to programmers. DevOps engineers and automation testers often find this concept vital in preparing for interviews. Shell scripting allows the development of simple to complex scripts. A number of daily tasks can be automated using shell scripting as well. We thought of making your job easier by putting together an ensemble of the most frequently asked interview questions and sample answers on shell scripting. These interview questions will definitely help you understand that shell is basically an interface between the user and the operating system, which interprets user commands to be executed by the kernel or operating system. Useful Resources: Useful Resources: Unix Interview Unix Interview Automation Testing Interview Automation Testing Interview Devops Interview Devops Interview",
        "reference": "interviewbit.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "1) What is shell script?",
        "answer": "A shell script is a command containing text file that contains one or more commands.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "2) Why is the use of shell script?",
        "answer": "It is used by system administrators to issue numbers of commands to accomplish the task. All commands are added together in a text file (shell script) to complete daily routine tasks.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "3) What are the advantages of shell scripting?",
        "answer": "These are the two main advantages of shell scripting:\nADVERTISEMENT\nADVERTISEMENT\nIt facilitates you to develop your own operating system with relevant features best suited for you.\nYou can design software applications according to their platform.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "4) What are the disadvantages of shell scripting?",
        "answer": "Following are the main disadvantages of shell scripting:\nA weak design can destroy the entire process and could prove a costly error.\nIf a typing error occurs during the creation then it can delete the entire data as well as partition data.\nIts initial process is slow and improves gradually.\nPortability between different operating system is difficult.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "5) What are the different types of variables used in shell script?",
        "answer": "There are two types of variables used in shell script:\nSystem defined variables: These variables are defined or created by operating system itself.\nUser defined variables: These variables are defined by system users.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "6) What is the syntax of \"nested if statement\" in shell scripting?",
        "answer": "if [ Condition ]  \nthen  \ncommand1  \ncommand2  \n.....  \nelse  \nif [ condition ]  \nthen  \ncommand1  \ncommand2  \n.....  \nelse  \ncommand1  \ncommand2  \n.....",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "7) What is the use of \"$?\" sign in shell script?",
        "answer": "While writing the shell script, the \"$?\" sign is used with \"if statement\" to check whether the previous command is executed successfully or not.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "8) What is the use of break command?",
        "answer": "The break command is used to escape from a loop in progress.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "9) What is GUI scripting?",
        "answer": "GUI stands for Graphical User Interface. It is used for controlling a computer and its applications. GUI scripting supports different applications. It mostly depends on the operating system.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "10) What are the various stages of a Linux process it passes through?",
        "answer": "A Linux process generally passes through four stages:\nWaiting: In this stage, the Linux process waits for resource.\nRunning: In this stage, the Linux process is currently being executed.\nStopped: In this stage, the Linux process is stopped after successful execution.\nZombie: This stage is known as zombie because the process has stopped but still active in process table.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "11) Is it possible to substitute \"ls\" command in the place of \"echo\" command?",
        "answer": "Yes.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "12) What is the syntax of while loop in shell scripting?",
        "answer": "The while loop is used to repeat its block of commands a number of times. It is different from for loop, it iterates until the while condition is no longer true.\nwhile [ test_condition ]  \ndo  \ncommands...  \ndone",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "13) What is the difference between soft and hard links?",
        "answer": "Inode: Each file contains an index number known as \"inode\" which is comprised of metadata about the associated file.\n\nHard Link: is the mirror of original linked file. In such case, hard link and original file contains same inode. Hard link remains linked whether original file is removed.\n\nSoft Link: is like shortcut feature of Windows OS. In such case, hard link and original file contains different inode. Soft link will not work correctly if original file is removed.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "14) What is the use of \"$#\" in Shell Scripting?",
        "answer": "The $# shows total number of arguments passed to the script.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    },
    {
        "question": "15) What are the Zombie processes?",
        "answer": "Zombie processes are the processes which are died but exit status is not picked by the parent process.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "shell-scripting"
    }
]